All right.
Hello, I'm Nick Montfort.
My thanks to the Yellow Conference team
and to all of you for joining me today.
I'll be speaking about a research project
at the two institutions
I'm affiliated with, MIT's Trope Tank and
the center for Digital Narratives, center
for the center
for Digital Narrative
at the University of Bergen in Norway.
I'll introduce this
Narrative Knobs project, and I'll give you
one hint of the research
result we have at this point.
So here's how we'll proceed.
First, a short
discussion of what a story generator
is with a bit of historical context,
then an introduction
to the project overall.
And after that I'll look at four
abstracted reimplementation
or sketches or nubs
that we've developed so far.
And finally,
a little about one research result
we obtained so far,
which is a nuanced understanding
of how the story worlds of these four
generators are organized as universes.
That is, their cosmologies.
I'll just contrast the cosmologies
of two generators in today's
brief presentation.
So to begin with,
some examples of story generation,
just two of them in context.
But context is a very broad
historical one.
This is a timeline by my collaborator
Jacob Cosmic.
And beginning in 1960,
when there was a sort of demo developed
by MIT programmers for a CBS documentary,
there's been a huge amount of activity
in Story Generation
for many different purposes.
A lot of it has been research based,
and if you read survey papers,
you'll find a lot of the regular sorts
of usual suspects.
But there's many other sorts of systems
as well.
And to give you an idea of what a story
generator is from our perspective,
I'll start off and turn
to probably
the most canonical of them all,
tailspin by James Meehan system
that he published his dissertation
about in 1976.
It's known for generating stories
about anthropomorphic animals
who are trying to satisfy their
hungers, for instance, and and be able.
Joe Bear is looking for some honey
and so forth,
but it actually can generate
other sorts of stories as well.
And here it's not Jobert,
but Joe Newton and Maggie Smith,
who are working to satisfy
a different need.
At the base of Maslow's hierarchy.
They were horny
and needed to get together.
Tailspin is also famous
for coming up with Miss Spun Tales
like this one.
Gravity was implemented as a character,
so gravity drowned
when it fell into the river.
And these are interesting examples
that neon writes about in his thesis,
and they're probably actually more famous
in many ways than the successful stories
came out of tailspin.
Although tailspin did influence The Sims,
Richard Evans based some of the character
generation or character development
and behavior
on Tailspin Story Machine.
Now let's set the Wayback Machine
for 1983.
Is an attainment piece of software,
actually seven different pieces
of software for seven different platforms.
And here we see the Commodore 64 version,
one of three
that runs on its own
generating these stories.
I've turned off the sound,
but there's leap motifs that go with
each of the different sorts of objects
these animistic pan
actors
who are going around and doing stuff.
So to
put those back in context,
we see on already
a variety of different art
projects, commercial projects
and research projects in the first half
of this timeline, and then from 1990 on,
a lot of additional activity,
which is still ongoing.
Now to introduce
the Narrative Nubs project.
Our project is to develop systematic
and abstract re re implementations
of these story generators, story
generators of these sorts.
And there are six of us, Yuka
being the lead on the project
now and programing that after work
by four others and my having founded this
and worked with Louis
and Daniel quite a while ago, and Michel
and more recently
the project is
located
here.
In the chat
I've pasted the URL on Koeberg,
which is a development platform very much
like GitHub, except community based.
So the idea at a very high level
is we take an existing story
generator like story machine,
and we develop our abstract
reimplementation
of it as freely bourbon source software
that anyone can use.
And in the process
of doing this, we learned some things.
There's no generative AI involved.
Since we've been talking about
AI a lot at yellow 2026, the systems
we study are in many cases AI systems,
but they're good old fashioned AI systems.
Go find we're not studying
any gen AI systems,
and we're not using gen AI to write code.
Claude is not a member of our team,
and despite the track,
there's no relationship to hypertext.
Also,
a miniature now is a related concept
a small scale version of a computer system
with the essentials.
So Roger Schank
had his students develop these miniatures,
and in fact, Mian did one for tailspin.
But there's been many other tailspin
implementations that have been done
over the years,
and we implementations of other systems.
What we're doing that's different
is creating a systematic set
of reimplementation, and they're meant
to be abstract, capture the essence.
So they're miniature like,
but not by the original developers.
They're in Python three,
a widely used language.
They share libraries that we developed.
Their coded in a consistent style,
and they're more concise,
more concise than the originals.
Now, this all has certain instrumental
purposes because we make this available.
We have a version one release already and
people can use it for future research.
They can integrate and modify the knobs,
they can use it in teaching and learning,
and they can make nubs
the basis of new artistic projects.
But abstracted
reimplementation is itself research.
The general concept
is programing as inquiry.
But more specifically, what
we're conducting is what your neighbor
described as rational reconstruction,
helping us move from knowhow
and implicit understanding of yeah,
we know what tailspin does.
We know what Story
Machine does to know what
explicit knowledge
of how its rules functioned.
Abstraction also compels us to determine
what's essential about these systems
from our perspective,
and this compels a better understanding
of these existing story systems.
So here is an overview of what we've done.
A diagram that Jacob produced showing
that we have so far
four nubs, gesture Taylor, Story Machine
and Through the Park.
Two of these share
a library a realized that transforms
abstract sentence
representations into surface text.
And these nubs are based on systems
of very different sorts.
So let me tell you
a little bit about what they are.
You saw Story Machine,
but what our nub of it does is in
many ways quite an extreme extraction
and an extreme abstraction,
because we're interested in presenting
text based story generation.
We've left aside all the animation,
the sound, the
the iconography,
what's on screen or off screen,
and we've simply taken
the sentences that are generated.
And that's our abstraction of what Story
Machine does.
In the nub for gesture.
We have a text based system to begin with,
and we've tried to understand it
with reference to the extensive work
that Lim Pemberton did.
More than one advanced degree
about this, modeling
the structure of old French epics,
and then building a specific story
generator
that operationalized those ideas.
So here's the beginning
of one complex story that our gesture nub
has generated
about one of these old French epic heroes
seeking a woman and going to assault
a city in order to capture
the Taylor
nub models a system from 1991 by
Smith and Whitten that has anthropomorphic
animals in the tundra.
And you can see that sometimes
things turn out better or worse.
Or in this case, the Arctic turn. Truman.
It's a game playing model
using the minimax algorithm,
and the last model is one
based on ellipses.
It's an extremely simple system
that I developed in 2008, but it's across
four languages, and that may make it
a little more interesting.
And I'll just hint at the cosmology
of two of these story worlds
as being something that we understood
better through our existing process.
So there's a great chain of being
that I'm going to tell you
about in about 15 seconds.
It holds all throughout the Middle Ages,
for instance,
that things that have more properties
are better than things with fewer God,
better than angels, better than humans,
better than non-human animals,
better than plants, better than rocks.
So which of these different types
of story universes are more in line
with the great chain of being?
And when we get down to nuance, how is it
that they resisted or embrace it?
So jester, of course,
being based on the old French epic,
actual medieval literature
is quite related to this.
And one of the things we did
in implementing the system is to model
God as a first order entity
within the system,
because the characters praise God after
they've been successful at their conquest.
On the other hand, Story Machine very much
resists the great chain of being.
It's a lexical system
in which all sorts of things can happen.
Any actor is as likely to perform
an action
that's intransitive
or on some other action,
so the boy can eat the apple
as easily as the apple can eat the boy.
There
are a few
exceptions, and working with the system
so far has helped us to locate
what those are and to see
how this flattened cosmology is not total.
So that's what I've got for you today.
I went a little over time,
but we did go through some examples
of story generation and introduction
to rather extensive project,
the four knobs we have
and the cosmology of story worlds.
Thank you for your patience and attention.